so let's talk about hemocromatosis
this is such an important subject
especially in Europe and I'm going to
explain why First Let Me Def Define the
term hemocromatosis hemocromatosis
basically means iron overload it
basically means that so you can get to
iron overload or hemoc comatosis by two
ways either genetic or hereditary
hemocromatosis or non- gentic factors
and the genetic factors when I was in
med school in the 1990s they told us
that hereditary hemocromatosis was a
very rare disease yes uh they only found
out about the genetics where the the
gene mutation happened in the 90s so I
remember when I was in med school that
they came up this big thing that oh my
God they found the Gene and it's called
the HF Gene that's where most of the
mutations happen so there's three
different U mutations there's the HF
there's the c282 Y so if somebody did
their 23 and me they will get all your
genes all your Snips um you can do any
other genetic places and go and look for
those so there's three mutations that
can affect ion physiology and cause
hemocromatosis
hereditary hemocromatosis the most
common H c282 white
mutation second most common is
h63d and they even found a third one now
recently
s65c but the first two are the first two
most important ones the more
um dangerous one is the first one c282y
and if you have a homozygous meaning
boths you got it from both of your
parents it's a recessive trait you need
to get it from both of your parents
that's when you have true pathologic
hematosis and that's what most
hematology is focus on people who are he
homozygous for the c282 white HF Gene
those people have a high risk of
developing iron overload or
hemocromatosis and those people can have
um there was a Triad that I learn in med
school they have diabetes because iron
deposits in the pancreas they get
curosis because it deposits in the liver
and they get Bron
skin skin so it affects their skin a lot
so that Triad was always in almost in
every B question what's that Triad
hereditary hemocromatosis so now we
found the Gene and it is way more common
than than I thought so in the US homo
zyus c2a T affects about 0.5% of the
population 0.5 or 3 million it's a good
amount so we think there's 1.5 million
of people with homozygous sosis that are
not diagnosed and that there's a high
possibility of iron overload then you
can have heterozygous c282 I so if you
heterozygous the hematologist will tell
you you don't have hemocromatosis you're
only a carrier and this is where I
completely disagree and the studies are
showing that this is not true even if
you have one Gene and you are put put in
an environment where there's too much
iron if you drink alcohol and if you do
other things like for example
testosterone increases iron stores if
you take supplements that have too much
iron even one gene out of the two can
predispose you to have a higher level
and I'm going to give you a quick little
example of a patient that I saw is
actually from Belgium no I'm sorry Le
from from the UK then lived in Belgium
and he developed diabetes at the age of
35 but he drink Dr a lot of alcohol
almost four to eight pints of beer from
the age of 15 so in 20 years he always
did that never had problem developed
severe diabetes A1C difficult to control
at 35 20 years of drinking and you know
they told him yes the alcohol it could
be no genetic predisposition they didn't
know and his main symptoms was fatigue
chronic fatigue and joint pains diabetes
doesn't give you that much chronic
fatigue and joint pains when I saw him
after he saw so many patients I checked
his iron his fertin was about 800 is
remember less than 400 is what's normal
optimal less than 100 his ion saturation
transfer saturation was 60% should be
less than
50 so right there I was like you have an
iron
problem uh but drinking alcohol by
itself can increase your fertin then I
sent him for the genetic testing and he
had one out of the two Al I sent him to
a hematologist the hematologist was like
no when you have one you don't absorb
ion I called the hematologist I told him
I don't agree he has high iron yes maybe
the environment of drinking a lot of
alcohol expressed that phenotype but he
had it because he had high iron and now
the high iron not only affected his
pancreas we checked his liver he had
fatty liver we checked his testosterone
he had low te because iron accumulates
the first place it usually accumulate
it's in the pancreas the Li and the
pituitary so iron will deposit in the
interior pituitary where the gonado TRS
are gonado TRS are what secrete L and
FSH so as we get more iron it it
decreases your LH and FSH so high iron
is very tightly um linked to low
testosterone secondary
hypogonadism infertility and Ed so
what's bad with the deposits of iron in
the pituitary it happens early they've
done study autopsy studies because we
don't have any MRI that can detect that
and they've seen that even from the age
of 30 years old in the general
population
ion starts depositing in the pituitary
and that's how it decreases your your
testosterone long term so pituitary ion
is really really important there's no
way to check for it but high iron so
this patient what I did with him I put
him on a on a plan of blood donation
once his ftin went below 300 felt so
much better his chronic fatigue improved
his joint pains improved his diabetes
was improving you know he still needs
all of the treatment unfor fortunately
with him we checked what they call a c
peptide and it showed that it was such
an aggressive diabetes his body was not
making any more insulin when it comes to
his testosterone also same thing a lot
of times when it's long-standing ion
toxicity you may not be able to reverse
it because it's been deposited so long
it causes fibrosis yeah so this guy had
diabetes um fatty liver low testosterone
abnormal sperm count and erect problems
what was the root cause of all this iron
overload yeah if you if that patient
came to see me three years ago I would
say the root cause of all this is low
testost but we need to go deeper when we
went deeper we saw so a lot of patients
may be diagnosed with all of those other
things and we never go to the iron so
iron is really really important so let's
go back to hemocromatosis so you have
the C2 a2i heterozygous or homozygous
h63d this tends to be a a better
prognosis if you have this whether it's
homozygous or azygous you tend to have
less iron absorption and the last one is
s65c so when you do your your your Gene
testing you look at if you have a
variant in any of those once you look at
the variant now you look at your iron
Labs because it doesn't matter what your
Gene say you need to know what's in your
blood when you put them together you
have a better idea um another example
that I have this guy was from Finland
this guy was homozygous for c282 I he
had both a his ftin was in a thousand
when he was diagnosed and he's been
donating blood his F usually is the 120s
now try I told him to try to get it
below 100 but this guy because he's
always always has a really good
lifestyle never drink alcohol he's was
62 he has muscles on him uh he eats well
because he's from um Finland he was
doing SAA three to four times a year
that's been shown to help with iron
overload he had no
disease although his Fatin on diagnosis
was a thousand he's he's never had
diabetes never had low tea because he's
he was diagnosed in his early 30s before
iron overload caused the damage so it
doesn't so you could think that this guy
was homo zygous he's going to have worse
disease than the guy that was her zygus
all depends on the environment also yeah
okay so very interesting and if we think
about European patients in northern
Europe it's about there's way more
prevalence of hemocromatosis Gene we
think that it originated in the Viking
area and it's called actually the Celtic
curse because it's northern European
ancestry although it's disseminated
throughout the world but you look at for
example in Ireland the incidence of
having c28 to Y one out of the two is
about
20% general population in the UK is
about 10 to 12% so there's about 12% of
people in the UK who may have one gene
for hemoc and they don't know that the
more you drink alcohol the more iron you
accumulate so for some people even two
or three pints with a gene for hematosis
is bad so anybody should know their iron
status especially if you have northern
European incestry so this is genetic or
hereditary hosis but you can have
nonhereditary
hum meaning that you have iron overload
without having any genes for it first
what discovering what genes are coding
for this we just found out a third Gene
recently we may found out more genes in
the future but let's say you check your
levels your fertin is 500 your iron
saturation is 52% your genes are
completely normal you still have iron
overload what may be causing it it may
be that you're taking too much iron in
your diet it may be that you take things
that suppress Heiden testosterone being
one of them if you take testosterone and
growth hormone the suppress have siden
because they want to make muscle grow
it's an anabolic treatment so remember
that relationship when you suppress
Heiden the the the the lines of iron
absorption are wide open so you may have
a high or normal iron storage but you
keep increase your absorbing from your
diet and you keep recycling for your
macras in your spleen so all when you
take testosterone growth hormone and
other things like this suppresses your
Heiden you have a continued increase of
iron despite normal stories I think for
everybody on testosterone right now they
need to hear that again testosterone
suppresses Heiden
homison level so testosterone causes
physiologic hemocromatosis and this is a
paper that was done by Dr lipshultz and
Dr um grenson I think published in 2018
and I will have that in my class um the
name of it is iron and sex hormones the
Good the Bad and the Ugly and that was
the first paper actually contacted them
and they were like it surprised them
also we knew that relationship again
Heiden was only discovered in 2001 but
once that is now there anybody taking
testone has a low level of idon and will
absorb more iron so I looked at my iron
over the past six years that I've been
on testal my Fatin was usually in the 80
to 120 range and it went up to the 300
so I donate blood two to three times a
year finally I got my fertin below 100
you want to check your levels two months
after you donate so I donate every four
months more or less I check my iron
levels usually on the third month and
based on where that is I decide if I'll
do an extra donation or not and I'm
maintaining my fairity now below 100 120
sometime it goes down to 60 but it's
funny and I followed my iron the past
three years and I steadily climbed and
now that I know about iron I try not to
eat a lot of carbs that are fortified
with iron I eat a good amount of red
meat but I don't get much iron from
other places but I've had a steady climb
and with those studies I told you I want
to keep my ferin below 200 so when you
think about hemocromatosis or iron
overload it's either you have hereditary
hemocromatosis or you can have
nonhereditary
hematosis and if somebody finds that
they have nonhereditary ion overload or
hemocromatosis
we need to try to figure out where you
getting extra iron from um Centrum the
most used multivitamin in the US has 18
milligram of iron in most protein shakes
protein bars have about 18 to 25
milligrams of iron in it so the RDA
daily allowance is 8 milligram let's say
a multivitamin and a protein bar you
already at almost 35 40 grams of
milligrams of iron you're already taking
too much iron so you can accumulate if
you take testost you will see a steady
climb on your test on your iron if you
take growth hormone a lot of those
things on birth control pills increases
iron so there are so many things and I
have all the list so for me my after
reading all of this what I do for myself
and I recommend for my patients know
your iron status based on those studies
I want your fertin to be less than 100
and your iron saturation to be not low
between 20 to 50 20 to 45 because when
you have a good iron saturation it means
you still have enough iron for the
essential functions of iron very
balanced then I take enough antioxidants
to make sure that any RS or oxidation
that I have I get and and those things
we talked about we know about the
importance of antioxidant and I monitor
those blood tests but everybody should
know their iron status even more if you
on testosterone even more if you have
northern European descent you should
know your iron
status awesome information thank you so
much for sharing yes uh new to me yes
yes and let me talk again about blood
donation really quick so usually people
are are worried about blood donation so
blood donation is a very easy procedure
um in in the US we have the Red Cross we
have a private organization called one
blood that's mostly where I go and in
the US they take out about 450 ml per
donation usually from that you will lose
about 25 to 50 25 to 30 milligrams of
iron um So based on how high your fertin
is you can calculate how many donations
you will need to bring your fertin down
they allow you to donate usually every
50 every two months so you could donate
six times a year most people don't need
that much the studies are showing that
frequent blood donors two to three times
a year that's when usually it's best and
you monitor your Fatin I tell patients
do not donate blindly and something
interesting also when you go to the Red
Cross or one blood they will check your
blood to let you know if you can donate
and they will usually tell you your iron
level is 15 you're okay to donate it's
not the iron level that they're checking
they're checking the hemoglobin level
that's usually between 12 and 16 um if
you below 13 they won't let you donate
but the the the employees there keep
saying we check your iron it's your
hemoglobin to check your iron you need
to request iron tibc and fertin yeah
again blood donation is very easy uh you
want to make sure that you stay well
hydrated most people tolerate that well
um
and yeah so on patients that we need to
donate more often I usually have them
donate every two months and monitor the
levels my patients who have fa of
thousand and plus I usually will send
them to my hematologist consultant
because they can donate every week every
two days as long as you monitor your
level that you don't go below that level
so and again what's important for blood
donation you do something good for you
and you do something good for the for
for the
world